<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<component type="desktop">
  <id>org.pythonscad.OpenSCAD</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <name>OpenSCAD</name>
  <summary>The Programmers Solid 3D CAD Modeller</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="de">The Programmers Solid 3D CAD Modeller</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="fr">Le modeleur CAO 3D des programmeurs</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ka">Solid 3D CAD მოდელერი პროგრამისტებისთვის</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="pl">Programistyczny CAD do bryłowego modelownia 3D</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ru">Твердотельная 3D-САПР для программистов</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="tr">Programcılar Katı 3B CAD Modelleyici</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="uk">Твердотільна тривимірна САПР для програмістів</summary>
  <icon type="remote">https://www.openscad.org/images/openscad.png</icon>
  <categories>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <category>3DGraphics</category>
  </categories>
  <url type="homepage">https://www.openscad.org/</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/openscad/openscad/issues</url>
  <url type="faq">https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/OpenSCAD_User_Manual/FAQ</url>
  <url type="help">https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/OpenSCAD_User_Manual</url>
  <url type="donation">https://www.openscad.org/community.html</url>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">openscad.desktop</launchable>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0+</project_license>
  <description>
    <p>OpenSCAD is a software for creating solid 3D CAD models. Unlike most free software for creating 3D models (such as Blender) it does not focus on the artistic aspects of 3D modelling but instead on the CAD aspects. Thus it might be the application you are looking for when you are planning to create 3D models of machine parts but pretty sure is not what you are looking for when you are more interested in creating computer-animated movies.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">OpenSCAD is a software for creating solid 3D CAD models. Unlike most free software for creating 3D models (such as Blender) it does not focus on the artistic aspects of 3D modelling but instead on the CAD aspects. Thus it might be the application you are looking for when you are planning to create 3D models of machine parts but pretty sure is not what you are looking for when you are more interested in creating computer-animated movies.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">OpenSCAD est un logiciel pour créer des modèles 3D (CAD). Contrairement à la plupart des logiciels libres de modélisation 3D (comme Blender) il ne se focalise pas sur l'aspect artistique de la modélisation mais plutôt sur les aspects de conception (CAD). Par conséquent, il peut être l'outil que vous recherchez lorsque vous voulez créer des modèles 3D pour des pièces de machines, mais il n'est certainement pas adapté si vous êtes intéressé par la création de films d'animation 3D.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hy">OpenSCAD- ը 3D CAD մոդելներ ստեղծելու ծրագիր է: Ի տարբերություն 3D մոդելների ստեղծման համար նախատեսված շատ անվճար ծրագրաշարի (օրինակ ՝ Blender), այն չի կենտրոնանում 3D մոդելավորման գեղարվեստական բաղադրիչի վրա, փոխարենը ՝ CAD ֊ի: Այսպիսով, սա կարող է լինել այն ծրագիրը, որը փնտրում եք, երբ նախատեսում եք ստեղծել մեքենայական մասերի 3D մոդելներ, բայց միանգամայն համոզված ենք, որ այն ձեզ պետք չի գա, եթե ավելի շատ հետաքրքրված եք համակարգչային անիմացիոն կերպարների/ կինոնկարների ստեղծմամբ:</p>
    <p xml:lang="ka">OpenSCAD მყარი 3D CAD მოდელების შექმნის პროგრამაა. სხვა 3D მოდელების შექმნის პროგრამებისგან განსხვავებით (მაგ: Blender), მისი ფოკუსი ხელოვნის 3D მოდელირების მაგიერ CAD-ის ასპექტებზეა. ამიტომ ის შეიძლება იყოს ის აპლიკაცია, რომელსაც ეძებთ, როცა გეგმავთ შექმნათ 3D მოდელები მანქანის ნაწილებისთვის, მაგრამ დარწმუნებული ბრძანდებოდეთ, რომ ეს ის არაა, რასაც ეძებთ, თუ კომპიუტერით ანიმაციური ფილმების შექმნა გნებავთ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">OpenSCAD jest programem CAD do bryłowego modelowania 3D. W przeciwieństwie do większości darmowego oprogramowania do tworzenia w 3D (np. Blender) nie skupia się na artystycznych aspektach modelowania 3D, lecz na aspektach CAD. Całkiem możliwe, że jeżeli chcesz stworzyć elementy maszyn, to jest to program dla ciebie. Z drugiej strony, na pewno nie jest tym czego szukasz, jeżeli jesteś zainteresowany tworzeniem filmów animowanych komputerowo.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ru">OpenSCAD — это приложение для создания трёхмерных моделей САПР. В отличие от большинства аналогичных свободных программ (например, Blender), в OpenSCAD основной упор сделан не на художественных аспектах моделирования, а на автоматизации проектирования. Другими словами, OpenSCAD больше подходит для изготовления трёхмерных моделей механизмов, чем для создания компьютерной анимации. </p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">OpenSCAD, katı 3B CAD modelleri oluşturmak için bir yazılımdır. 3B modeller oluşturmaya yönelik çoğu ücretsiz yazılımın (Blender gibi) aksine, 3B modellemenin sanatsal yönlerine değil, CAD yönlerine odaklanır. Bu nedenle, makine parçalarının 3B modellerini oluşturmayı planlarken aradığınız uygulama olabilir, ancak bilgisayar ile animasyonlu filmler oluşturmakla daha çok ilgilendiğinizde aradığınız şey bu değildir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">OpenSCAD це програмне забезпечення для створення твердотільних 3D моделей. На відміну від більшості вільного ПЗ для створення 3D моделей (такого як Blender) він не зосереджується на мистецьких аспектах моделювання, замість цього - на аспектах САПР. Тому це може бути програма, яку ви шукаєте коли плануєте створювати 3D моделі запчастин механізмів, але зовсім не те що ви шукали, плануючи створення анімаційних фільмів.</p>
    <p>OpenSCAD is not an interactive modeller. Instead it is something like a 3D-compiler that reads in a script file that describes the object and renders the 3D model from this script file. This gives you (the designer) full control over the modelling process and enables you to easily change any step in the modelling process or make designs that are defined by configurable parameters.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">OpenSCAD is not an interactive modeller. Instead it is something like a 3D-compiler that reads in a script file that describes the object and renders the 3D model from this script file. This gives you (the designer) full control over the modelling process and enables you to easily change any step in the modelling process or make designs that are defined by configurable parameters.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">OpenSCAD n'est pas un modeleur interactif. Au contraire, il s'agit d'un genre de compilateur 3D, qui lit un script décrivant l'objet à modéliser et qui construit un modèle 3D à partir de ce script. Cela vous donne (en tant que concepteur) un contrôle total du processus de modélisation et vous permet de modifier facilement n'importe quelle étape de la modélisation ou de produire des conceptions qui sont définies selon des paramètres éditables.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hy">OpenSCAD- ը ինտերակտիվ մոդերատոր չէ: Փոխարենը այն 3D կազմողի պես մի բան է, որը կարդում է օբյեկտը նկարագրող սցենարի նիշքը  և այս սցենարի նիշքից ներկայացնում է 3D մոդելը: Սա ձեզ (դիզայներին) լիակատար վերահսկողություն է տալիս մոդելավորման գործընթացի վրա և հնարավորություն է տալիս հեշտությամբ փոխել մոդելավորման գործընթացում կատարված ցանկացած քայլ կամ կատարել այնպիսի ձևավորումներ, որոնք որոշվում են կարգավորելի պարամետրերով:</p>
    <p xml:lang="ka">OpenSCAD -ი ინტერაქტიურ მოდელერს არ წარმოადგენს. ის უფრო 3D კომპილატორის მსგავსი პროგრამაა, რომელიც ობიექტის აღწერის სკრიპტის ფაილების კითხულობს და მათგან 3D მოდელებს გენერირებს. ეს თქვენ (დიზაინერს) მოდელირების პროცეზე სრულ კონტროლს და მოდელირების ნებისმიერ საფეხურზე ჩარევის საშუალებას გაძლევთ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">OpenSCAD nie służy do interaktywnego modelowania. Jest czymś w rodzaju kompilatora 3D, który czyta skrypt opisujący obiekt i na tej podstawie renderuje model. Daje to pełną kontrolę nad procesem modelowania i pozwala na proste wprowadzanie zmian na każdym etapie projektowania. Pozwala także tworzyć obiekty, które są definiowane za pomocą konfigurowalnych parametrów.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ru">OpenSCAD не является интерактивным редактором моделей. Это скорее компилятор, который считывает описывающий объект скрипт и отрисовывает соответствующую модель. Это расширяет возможности моделирования и позволяет легко изменить любой из этапов этого процесса. Вы можете создавать любые модели на основе настраиваемых параметров.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">OpenSCAD etkileşimli bir modelleyici değildir. Bunun yerine, nesneyi tanımlayan bir komut dosyasında okuyan ve bu komut dosyasından 3B modeli işleyen bir 3B derleyici gibi bir şeydir. Bu size (tasarımcıya) modelleme süreci üzerinde tam kontrol sağlar ve modelleme sürecindeki herhangi bir adımı kolayca değiştirmenize veya yapılandırılabilir parametrelerle tanımlanan tasarımlar yapmanıza olanak tanır.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">OpenSCAD це не інтерактивний моделер. Замість цього це щось на зразок 3D-компілятору який читає скриптовий файл, у якому описано модель, та будує 3D модель зі скриптового файлу. Це дає вам (розробнику) повний контроль над процесом конструювання та дозволяє легко змінити будь-який крок в процесі моделювання, або розробляти моделі, які повністю визначені через конфігураційні параметри.</p>
    <p>OpenSCAD provides two main modelling techniques: First there is constructive solid geometry (aka CSG) and second there is extrusion of 2D outlines. As data exchange format for this 2D outlines Autocad DXF files are used. In addition to 2D paths for extrusion it is also possible to read design parameters from DXF files. Besides DXF files OpenSCAD can read and create 3D models in the STL and OFF file formats.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">OpenSCAD provides two main modelling techniques: First there is constructive solid geometry (aka CSG) and second there is extrusion of 2D outlines. As data exchange format for this 2D outlines Autocad DXF files are used. In addition to 2D paths for extrusion it is also possible to read design parameters from DXF files. Besides DXF files OpenSCAD can read and create 3D models in the STL and OFF file formats.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">OpenSCAD permet deux techniques principales de modélisation: D'abord il y a la construction de solides géométriques "constructive solid geometry" (CSG) et ensuite l'extrusion des schémas 2D. Le format d'échange de ces schémas 2D est le format de fichier Autocad DXF. En complément aux schémas 2D pour l'extrusion il est aussi possible de lire les paramètres des fichiers DXF. En sus des fichiers DXF, OpenSCAD peut lire et créer des modèles 3D aux formats STL et OFF.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hy">OpenSCAD- ը տրամադրում է մոդելավորման երկու հիմնական տեխնիկա. Նախ կա կառուցողական ամուր երկրաչափություն (aka CSG), երկրորդը `2D ուրվագծերի արտահոսքն է: Որպես այս 2D ուրվագծերի տվյալների փոխանակման ձևաչափ ՝ օգտագործվում են Autocad DXF նիշքեր: Բացի արտածման համար 2D ուրվագծերից հնարավոր է նաև կարդալ դիզայնի կարգաբերումները DXF նիշքերից: Բացի DXF նիշքերից, OpenSCAD- ը կարող է կարդալ և ստեղծել 3D մոդելներ STL և OFF նիշքերի ձևաչափերով:</p>
    <p xml:lang="ru">OpenScad предлагает два основных метода моделирования: конструктивная сплошная геометрия и экструзия. Для задания двухмерных контуров используются файлы Autocad DXF. В дополнение к двухмерному пути экструзии, возможно чтение проектных параметров из файлов DX. Помимо файлов DXF, OpenSCAD может читать и создавать 3D-модели в форматах STL и OFF.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">OpenSCAD iki ana modelleme tekniği sunar: Birincisi yapıcı katı geometri (aka CSG) ve ikincisi 2B anahatların ekstrüzyonu vardır. Bu 2B anahatlar için veri alışverişi formatı olarak Autocad DXF dosyaları kullanılır. Ekstrüzyon için 2B yollara ek olarak, DXF dosyalarından tasarım parametrelerini okumak da mümkündür. DXF dosyalarının yanı sıra OpenSCAD, STL ve OFF dosya formatlarında 3B modelleri okuyabilir ve oluşturabilir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">OpenSCAD забезпечує дві техніки моделювання: перша це Конструктивна блокова геометрія (або CSG), а друга це видавлювання 2D контурів. В якості формату обміну даних для цих 2D контурів використовуються файли AutoCAD DXF. Окрім файлів DXF OpenSCAD може читати та створювати 3D моделі у форматах файлів STL та OFF.</p>
  </description>
  <provides>
    <mediatype>application/x-pythonscad</mediatype>
  </provides>
  <developer_name>The OpenSCAD Developers</developer_name>
  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image type="source">https://www.openscad.org/images/appdata-screenshot-1.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image type="source">https://www.openscad.org/images/appdata-screenshot-2.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1"/>
  <releases>
    <release date="2021-01-31" version="2021.01"/>
    <release date="2019-05-16" version="2019.05"/>
    <release date="2016-02-22" version="2015.03-3"/>
    <release date="2015-11-15" version="2015.03-2"/>
    <release date="2015-04-21" version="2015.03-1"/>
    <release date="2015-03-10" version="2015.03"/>
    <release date="2014-03-09" version="2014.03"/>
    <release date="2013-06-18" version="2013.06"/>
    <release date="2013-01-17" version="2013.01"/>
    <release date="2011-12-29" version="2011.12"/>
  </releases>
</component>
